

SENIOR RESEARCHER

Wageningen Economic Research, Prinses Beatrixlaan 582, 2595 BM the Hague, the Netherlands

🛘 +31 70 3358 341 | 🗷 michiel.vandijk@wur.nl | 🏕 michielvandijk.org | 🖸 0000-0002-5207-7304 | 🔃 michiel_van_dijk | 🖸 michielvandijk

Profile

Michiel van Dijk is a development economist, with interest in the topics of macro and micro-level policy evaluation, land use change, food security and nutrition, integrated assessments, scenario development and modelling, technical change and innovation, and farm and household-level analysis. He has been a (lead) researcher in projects funded by CIMMYT, DFID, FCDO, GEF, USAID, World Bank and the EU. His skills include computable general equilibrium modelling, micro-econometrics, GIS and (big) data management. He has extensive working experience in Africa, Asia and Latin America.

Qualifications _____

Technology Management, Eindhoven University of TechnologyPH.D.1999-2004Economics, Universidad de ZaragozaSpainERASMUS EXCHANGE PROGRAMME1999Economics, Maastricht Universitythe NetherlandsM.Sc. IN QUANTITATIVE ECONOMICS1993-1999Economics, Maastricht Universitythe Netherlands

1995

Employment history _____

PROPEDEUSE IN ECONOMETRICS

Wageningen Economic Research	the Netherlands
Senior researcher	2020-
International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis (IIASA)	Austria
GUEST RESEARCH SCHOLAR	2020-
International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis (IIASA)	Austria
RESEARCH SCHOLAR (0.8 FTE)	2016-2020
Wageningen Economic Research	the Netherlands
Senior researcher (0.2 fte, out of office)	2016-2020
Wageningen Economic Research	the Netherlands
Senior researcher	2014-2015
Wageningen Economic Research	the Netherlands
RESEARCHER	2011-2013
Oxfam Novib	the Netherlands
WEST AFRICA ADVOCACY OFFICER	2008-2010
Centre for Research on Multinational Corporations (SOMO)	the Netherlands
RESEARCHER	2006-2008
Technology Management, Eindhoven University of Technology	the Netherlands
Assistant professor	2004-2005

Main research projects

Rapid landscape analysis of existing food security information and analysis work

Wageningen Economic Research

2021

LEAD RESEARCHER

• Design of research approach

· Analysis of agricultural information systems

Support for Modelling, Planning and Improving Dhaka's Food System

Wageningen Economic Research

2020-2022

Construction of spatial microsimulation model

Analysis of results

RESEARCHER

· Building of dashboard

Food Security Metrics Wageningen Economic Research

LEAD RESEARCHER 2018-2019

• Developing an approach to assess impact of fertilizer companies on food security

• Estimation of yield response functions using crop simulation results

• Combining company information with agro-economic analysis

Systematic review of global food security scenarios

Wageningen Economic Research

2017-2018

PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR

RESEARCHER

• Design of research approach

• Systematic review of global food security studies

Creation and analysis of global food security projections database

Integrated Solutions for Water, Energy, and Land (IS-WEL)

International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis

2016-2019

Analyzing large household surveys for Zambezi countries

Creation of high-resolution crop distribution maps

• Improving land use representation in GLOBIOM

African maize yield gap analysis Wageningen Economic Research

PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR 2015-2016

• Micro-econometric assessment of plot-level yield gaps

Analyzing large household surveys for Mali, Nigeria and Tanzania

Validation of CGE models Wageningen Economic Research

LEAD RESEARCHER 2013

• Developing an approach to validate multi-sector, multi-region CGE model results

Review of global food scenario studies

Wageningen Economic Research

PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR 2013

• Literature review of global food security scenario literature

Exploring the Future of Global Food and Nutrition Security

• Managing work package on participatory scenario development

Translation of stakeholder scenarios into model input

• Prepartion of explorative scenario database

Land use optimisation in Viet Nam: from Global to Local

PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR

Management of international research team

• Developing a participatory scenario and modelling approach

· Linking of CGE model with spatial land use model

Wageningen Economic Research

2012-2017

Wageningen Economic Research

2011-2012

WORK PACKAGE LEADER

Skills

Data Science R (advanced, e.g. package development)

Reproducible Research

Markdown/Rmarkdown, R shiny, R Flexdashboard, LaTeX, Git

Software

GEMPACK, GAMS, SPSS, STATA, E-views, C++, ArcGIS, QGIS, Microsoft Office

Dutch (native), English (fluent), German (good), Spanish (good), French (intermediate), Languages

Bahasa Indonesia (Working knowledge)

International working experience _

Various Ethiopia, Ghana, Malaysia, Vietnam, Zambia, Zimbabwe

RESEARCH PROJECTS

Various Nigeria, Mali, Burkina Faso, Ghana and Senegal

COOPERATION WITH LOCAL NGOS 2008-2010

A.C. Portachuelo Venezuela

ASSISTANT LOAN OFFICER (VOLUNTARY) 2005-2006

Science Policy Research Unit (SPRU), University of Sussex

EU MARIE CURIE PH.D. 2003-2004

United Kingdom

Indonesia

Statistics Finland Finland

VISITING RESEARCHER

Centre for Strategic and International Studies (CSIS) VISITING RESEARCHER 2001

Journal referee

Agricultural Systems, Agronomy, Agronomy for Sustainable Development, Environmental Research Letters, European Journal of Development Research, Global Food Security, Journal of African Economies, Journal of Engineering and Technology Management, Journal of Evolutionary Economics, Land, Scientific Reports.

Grants

I have acquired (often in collaboration with colleagues) about €1.1 million in external research grants since 2011.

2021	Rapid landscape analysis of existing food security information and analysis work. Funding from FCDO.	€8,800
2021	Research paper fund for paper on MAPSPAM. Funding from Wageningen Economic Research.	€10,000
2020-2021	Technical assistance on the implementation of the provisions on ILUC set out in the recast Renewable Energy Directive (N° ENER/C2/2018-462/LOT l/S12.821933). Funding from <i>EC DG Energy</i> .	€20,000
2020	Research paper fund for paper on food metrics. Funding from Wageningen Economic Research.	€10,000
2018–2019	Food Security metrics, designing innovative research methodology to assess the impact of agri-food companies on sustainable development. Funding from <i>UBS</i> .	€156,000
2018	Spatial Production Allocation Model (SPAM) for country analysis. Funding from IFPRI.	€32,800
2017-2018	Climate Smart Investment Plan Zambia. Funding from World Bank.	€49,200
2017-2018	Systematic review of global food security scenarios. Funding from John Hopkins University.	€41,000
2015–2017	Integrated assessment of the determinants of the maize yield gap in Sub-Saharan Africa (ES/LO12294/1). Funding from $DFID/ESRC$.	€458,780
2015-2016	African maize yield gap analysis. Funding from CIMMYT.	€123,000
2013	Review of global food scenario studies. Funding from Oxfam Novib.	€4,000
2012	Assessing the impact of climate change strategies on economic development, poverty and food security in Ghana (AID-OAA-A-13-00015). Funding from $USAID$.	€77,900
2011–2012	Land use optimisation in Viet Nam: from Global to Local (CDKN ALIF 2011-13). Funding from CDKN/DFID.	€135,600

Peer reviewed publications

- Dijk, M. van, Morley, T., Rau, M. L., & Saghai, Y. (2021). A meta-analysis of projected global food demand and population at risk of hunger for the period 2010–2050. *Nature Food*, 2(7), 494–501. https://doi.org/10.1038/s43016-021-00322-9
- Latka, C., Kuiper, M., Frank, S., Heckelei, T., Havlík, P., Witzke, H.-P., Leip, A., Cui, H. D., Kuijsten, A., Geleijnse, J. M., & Dijk, M. van. (2021). Paying the price for environmentally sustainable and healthy EU diets. *Global Food Security*, 28, 100437. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gfs.2020.100437
- Dijk, M. van, Morley, T., Loon, M. van, Reidsma, P., Tesfaye, K., & Ittersum, M. K. van. (2020). Reducing the maize yield gap in Ethiopia: Decomposition and policy simulation. *Agricultural Systems*, 183, 102828. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agsy.2020.102828
- Meijl, H. van, Shutes, L., Valin, H., Stehfest, E., Dijk, M. van, Kuiper, M., Tabeau, A., Zeist, W.-J. van, Hasegawa, T., & Havlik, P. (2020). Modelling alternative futures of global food security: Insights from FOODSECURE. *Global Food Security*, 25, 100358. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gfs.2020.100358
- Dijk, M. van, Gramberger, M., Laborde, D., Mandryk, M., Shutes, L., Stehfest, E., Valin, H., & Faradsch, K. (2020). Stakeholder-designed scenarios for global food security assessments. *Global Food Security*, 24, 100352. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gfs.2020.100352
- Johnson, N., Burek, P., Byers, E., Falchetta, G., Flörke, M., Fujimori, S., Havlik, P., Hejazi, M., Hunt, J., Krey, V., Langan, S., Nakicenovic, N., Palazzo, A., Popp, A., Riahi, K., Dijk, M. van, Vliet, M. T. H. van, Vuuren, D. P. van, Wada, Y., ... Parkinson, S. (2019). Integrated Solutions for the Water-Energy-Land Nexus: Are Global Models Rising to the Challenge? *Water*, 11(11), 2223. https://doi.org/10.3390/w11112223
- Wada, Y., Vinca, A., Parkinson, S., Willaarts, B. A., Magnuszewski, P., Mochizuki, J., Mayor, B., Wang, Y., Burek, P., Byers, E., Riahi, K., Krey, V., Langan, S., Dijk, M. van, Grey, D., Hillers, A., Novak, R., Mukherjee, A., Bhattacharya, A., ... Tong, J. (2019). Co-designing Indus Water-Energy-Land Futures. One Earth, 1(2), 185–194. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.oneear.2019.10.006
- Loon, M. P. van, Adjei-Nsiah, S., Descheemaeker, K., Akotsen-Mensah, C., Dijk, M. van, Morley, T., Ittersum, M. K. van, & Reidsma, P. (2019). Can yield variability be explained? Integrated assessment of maize yield gaps across smallholders in Ghana. *Field Crops Research*, 236, 132–144. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fcr.2019.03.022
- Frank, S., Havlik, P., Stehfest, E., Meijl, H. van, Witzke, P., Pérez-Domínguez, I., Dijk, M. van, Doelman, J. C., Fellmann, T., Koopman, J. F. L., Tabeau, A., & Valin, H. (2019). Agricultural non-CO2 emission reduction potential in the context of the 1.5 C target. *Nature Climate Change*, 9(1), 66–72. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41558-018-0358-8
- Meijl, H. van, Havlik, P., Lotze-Campen, H., Stehfest, E., Witzke, P., Domínguez, I. P., Bodirsky, B. L., Dijk, M. van, Doelman, J., Fellmann, T., Humpenöder, F., Koopman, J. F. L., Müller, C., Popp, A., Tabeau, A., Valin, H., & Zeist, W.-J. van. (2018). Comparing impacts of climate change and mitigation on global agriculture by 2050. *Environmental Research Letters*, 13(6), 064021. https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/aabdc4
- Smeets Kristkova, Z., Gardebroek, C., Dijk, M. van, & Meijl, H. van. (2017). The impact of R&D on factor-augmenting technical change an empirical assessment at the sector level. *Economic Systems Research*, 29(3), 385–417. https://doi.org/10.1080/09535314.2017. 1316707
- Dijk, M. van, Morley, T., Jongeneel, R., Ittersum, M. van, Reidsma, P., & Ruben, R. (2017). Disentangling agronomic and economic yield gaps: An integrated framework and application. *Agricultural Systems*, 154, 90–99. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agsy.2017.03.004
- Smeets Kristkova, Z., Dijk, M. van, & Meijl, H. van. (2017). Impact of agricultural R&D investments on long-term food security– an ex-ante impact assessment. In A. Schmitz (Ed.), Frontiers of economics and globalization.
- Smeets Kristkova, Z., Dijk, M. van, & Meijl, H. van. (2016). Projections of long-term food security with R&D driven technical change—A CGE analysis. NJAS Wageningen Journal of Life Sciences, 77(Supplement C), 39–51. https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.1016/j.njas.2016.03.001
- Dijk, M. van, & Meijerink, G. (2014). A review of global food security scenario and assessment studies: Results, gaps and research priorities. Global Food Security, 3(3-4), 227–238. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gfs.2014.09.004
- Rutten, M., Dijk, M. van, Rooij, W. van, & Hilderink, H. (2014). Land use dynamics, climate change, and food security in Vietnam: A global-to-local modeling approach. *World Development*, *59*, 29–46.
- Dijk, M. van, & Szirmai, A. (2011). The Micro-Dynamics Of Catch-Up In Indonesian Paper Manufacturing. *Review of Income and Wealth*, 57(1), 61–83.
- Weyzig, F., & Dijk, M. van. (2009). Incoherence between Tax and Development Policies: the case of the Netherlands. *Third World Quarterly*, 30(7), 1259–1277. http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/01436590903134916
- Dijk, M. van, & Bell, M. (2007). Rapid growth with limited learning: Industrial policy and indonesia's pulp and paper industry. Oxford Development Studies, 35(2), 149–169. https://doi.org/10.1080/13600810701322017
- Dijk, M. van, & Szirmai, A. (2006). Industrial Policy and Technology Diffusion: Evidence from Paper Making Machinery in Indonesia. *World Development*, 34(12), 2137–2152.
- Van Dijk, M., & Szirmai, A. (2006). Technical efficiency and embodied technical change in the Indonesian pulp and paper industry. *Journal of International Development*, 18(2), 163–178.
- Dijk, M. van. (2003). South African manufacturing performance in international perspective 1970-1999. South African Journal of Economics, 71(1), 119–142. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1813-6982.2003.tb00074.x

Book chapters

- Dijk, M. van, Saghai, Y., Morley, T., & Rau, M. L. (2020). Global food demand projections: A review. In A. Goldberg (Ed.), *Choose food: An ethical basis for food production*. John Hopkins University Press.
- Dijk, M. van, Kroezen, J., & Slob, B. (2018). From Pilsner Desert to Specialty Beer Oasis: The Rise of Microbrewing in the Netherlands. In J. Swinnen & C. Garavaglia (Eds.), *The craft beer revolution: A global economic perspective*. Palgrave Macmillan. https://www.palgrave.com/gp/book/9783319582344
- See, L., Fritz, S., Moorthy, I., Danylo, O., Dijk, M. van, & Ryan, B. (2018). Using Remote Sensing and Geospatial Information for Sustainable Development. In R. M. Desai, H. Kato, H. Kharas, & J. W. McArthur (Eds.), From summits to solutions: Innovations in implementing the sustainable development goals (pp. 172–198). Brookings Institution Press.
- Dijk, M. van, Moors, E. J., & Singh, T. (2014). Engaging stakeholders in developing food security scenarios. In T. Achterbosch (Ed.), *The food puzzle: Pathways to securing food for all* (pp. 40–42). Wageningen University.

Databases and code

- Dijk, M. van, Morley, T., Rau, M. L., & Saghai, Y. (2021). A meta-analysis of projected global food demand and population at risk of hunger for the period 2010–2050, data and scripts. https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5076072
- Dijk, M. van, Gramberger, M., Laborde, D., Mandryk, M., Shutes, L., Stehfest, E., Valin, H., & Zellmer, K. (2019). FOODSECURE Scenario Driver Database. https://doi.org/10.17026/dans-zeh-fd4m

Work in progress_

- Dijk, M. van, Wood-Sichra, U., Ru, Y., Palazzo, A., Havlik, P., & You, L. (2020). Generating multi-period crop distribution maps for Southern Africa using a data fusion approach.
- Dijk, M. van, Fuglie, K. O., & Heisey, P. W. (2018). A new database of public global agricultural R&D.
- Dijk, M. van, Smeets Kristkova, Z., & Gerber, N. (2018). A global index of Agricultural Innovation: Construction, ranking and application.